well good afternoon and thank you for
joining us for today's manulife business
success series
today we're going to be talking with
andy taylor
gore mutual insurance on 1839
startup transforming during covent
um it's going to be a fascinating
discussion for a company that that many
of you will have heard the name
uh in in the community for years and
years but how they're
adopting and changing their business
model in the middle of a pandemic is an
interesting story so
uh looking forward to this my name is of
course ian mclean
and i'm the president ceo of the greater
kitchener-waterloo chamber of commerce
before we get started i would like to
take a moment to acknowledge that we do
live and work
on the traditional territory of the
neutral anishinaabe
and hoda nishone peoples as we seek a
renewed relationship
based on the foundation of mutual
understanding and respect
as participants in today's virtual event
we are coming
together as one we believe everyone is
free to be their true self
and receive the same respect and
opportunity regardless of age
ethnicity gender culture identity sexual
orientation beliefs or language we hope
you will join us in fostering
a positive environment here today that
is a safe and welcoming space for all
we know there is more to do and we are
committed to listening
learning and growing as we go
today's session would not be possible
without the continued support of our
sponsors and so today a special thank
you to our
title sponsor for the business success
series manulife
our platinum sponsor for the series
which is the immigration partnership of
waterloo region
and in this month's presenting sponsor
gore mutual insurance
these organizations are committed to
supporting our local economy and
providing businesses with the resources
and tools they need
to thrive just before the session starts
i'd like to go over a couple of quick
reminders
please ensure that your microphone is
muted throughout the presentation
so we can reduce any background noise if
you have any questions that come up
through this session
please type them into the question box
in your control panel
if it's tech related one of our chamber
reps we'll get back to you right away
and if they're for today's spa presenter
i'll try and gather those throughout the
presentation and get them answered
throughout the course of the
presentation
all attendees will be sent a recording
of today's presentation and it will also
be made available
on the greater kw chamber website i
would like to now introduce today's
guest speaker
andy taylor and he is the chief
executive officer of gore mutual
insurance
canada's oldest mutual property and
casualty insurance company
he currently leads the company's next
horizon strategy which supports the
company's ambitious transformation to
become
a digitally led purpose-driven national
scale
insurer having worked with the board of
directors and the executive team to
develop the strategy over the last two
years
in his role as ceo he will oversee the
complete transformation of the company's
operating model
and technology platforms to create
best-in-class solutions
for brokers and customers andy joined
gorm mutual in 2005 and has held
progressive senior
roles within the organization most
recently holding the position of
cfo and chief risk officer at gore
where he's he was responsible for
strategic finance
investments reinsurance and risk
management he is currently a member of
the board of directors of gore
as well as chair of the board of
companies uh
subsidiary distribution business and a
member of the board of the institute for
catastrophic loss reduction
before coming to gore andy spent several
years working on the advisory teams for
several multinational
chartered professional accountant firms
he holds a ba
in uh in economics from western and is a
chartered professional accountant
join me in welcoming andy welcome andy
thank you ian i appreciate that uh
wonderful introduction
and uh just a pleasure to be here with
you today so thank you for having me
well i'm i'm you and i are old friends
we uh we've known each other for
a lot of years um we lived across the
street from my mom and dad
our daughters played volleyball so we
knew each other aside from business so
but it was a great opportunity when we
reconnected and you took over
at gore a couple of years ago uh to
to sort of have strength in the
relationship that we've always had
between
our chamber and and and gore um
so maybe talk a little bit about about
that relationship over the years i mean
the the chamber of commerce obviously
you're in cambridge you're physically
located in cambridge at the gore head
office
strong relationship with the cambridge
chamber but also had had uh a
a deeper relationship with uh with the
greater kw chamber
and in fact the region of water let's
start there about about gore and its
place in the region
yeah that's great thanks uh ian and i
think um
maybe worth even stepping back a bit
around
um you know our history in the region
and why that sort of
segues nicely into our relationship with
the chamber
um as you mentioned in the uh in the
introduction
you know we are canada's oldest uh
property and casualty insurance company
and we what that means is we sell home
and auto insurance and business
insurance
and at 181 years old we're actually
older than canada
and we were founded right here in this
community
in the district of gore and our
roots have been here for many years and
as a mutual insurance company
which is different from a stock based
company
we are effectively you know owned and
run by our members and our policyholders
many of who live in this community and
our founding members certainly did
and came together and so the view of a
mutual insurance company is really
very similar to a a peer-to-peer what
you hear about
in modern-day peer-to-peer organization
and
so we exist for a greater good than just
you know maximizing profit
um for shareholders value we we actually
exist to
really come together and care for each
other as members
and so you know that ties back to the
chamber and the great work that
your chamber and the cambridge chamber
have been doing over the years
we have always had a focus on really
giving back to and um contributing to
our community
uh whether it was through our company
directly or through our foundation we
have a very substantial foundation and
over the years we've worked with the
chamber and other organizations to
support the local hospitals local
charities and and important causes
so um you know to us uh the work that
we're doing and that you're doing in
this community is
is fundamental to you know where we've
come from as a company and where we're
going
which we'll share a lot today about our
transformation story
now a little bit about your background i
mean it's always interesting to see
where leaders come from i mean your
finance background but but maybe
talk a little bit about that the
importance of what you've learned those
skills bring
at this moment in gore's history because
it wouldn't always be the finance guy or
the risk guy
it may be other things that companies
need at different times
but now you were you were selected for a
variety of reasons talk
a little bit about your background and
what that um
brings to to to this change transfer or
this train
change agenda that you're bringing to
gore yeah
great question um i guess my personal
background too
links back to um to the community so i
was
uh born and raised in this area um grew
up in
in kitchener waterloo and then spent
half my life in toronto
in my teen years worked downtown for a
while and then i've been back for 20
years
and as you say i had a career in in
in finance and accounting but i always
worked in the insurance industry in the
practices of those firms
and my journey here at gore has been
really
an amazing one so one of the reasons i
love living in this community is the
balance that you get from
career opportunities that you know
combined with
quality of life and so we've raised a
family here
in the community as as you know but i've
also had the benefit of
career growth over those years and
tremendous opportunity
and so as you noted over the last um
eight years i was the chief financial
officer i've been with the company for
16 years so i've seen our organization
grow from a what we call a small
regional insurance company so 150
million in premiums
and if you think of our industry company
size might range from
100 million to as big as 12 billion
and today we're 500 million organization
over a billion in assets
in the time that i've been here and so i
think um
the skills i i bring into this new role
which for me is
um you know after 16 years like an
entirely new
you know job company and we'll talk some
more about that
um is that history of you know where
we've been as a company the financial
acumen to help us
um we're making significant investments
in the business
uh just to give you a perspective over
the course of the next two years
we're putting the same level of
investment in our transformation that we
normally would have done over a decade
um you know very so there's a financial
management piece to it that's sort of
natural for my background
but also i think um you know the the
experience i've had over the years i was
very fortunate in the last two years
to work directly with the board and
actually one of my direct colleagues to
shape our next horizon strategy
and um so i think i bring a
forward-looking view to
you know we've been around for 181 years
and we've been very successful but the
lens that we're looking at is
you know what do we need to do to
reinvent our organization and make sure
we're around for another 181 years
so even though sometimes finance and
accounting
types can be seen as relatively
conservative
you know i guess i've got a nice balance
of that with a forward-looking
lens on what's important for our
strategy going forward
and i'll share a bit about that in a
minute yeah so
i think that that's the story i wanted
to tell today and some people would say
insurance and they
go to sleep because insurance is not
necessarily the most exciting part
but i think the transformation story is
one that
everyone even if if you know what
they're watching this on
on the webcast down the road is every
business that has been in business and
needs to change should hear this story
because
it doesn't really matter the size of
your business but when you need to
change in that transformation
this is an important part of what what
what we wanted to get out today
and it's no different for chambers the
chamber world is changing
membership-based based organizations are
changing
and we have to change with it i think
covet has really
accelerated that maybe let's talk a
little bit about
the transformation and i would say it
covers just about everything you do it
almost is a complete transformation for
a company that has
what did you say 500 million in revenue
and a billion and a half under
under uh investment that's a side that's
a big
organization but you're doing a complete
transformation let's let's talk through
why that is and what what's involved
yeah it's a great um it's a great story
and and i think
a couple of key points you know in the
introduction and in the header we we
refer to ourselves as an 1839 startup
and and we love that term because i mean
we quite literally were founded in 1839
181 years ago but in many ways this
company is a startup again uh
you're right the scale of the
transformation is a complete rebuild of
the organization
and i think um again back to our mutual
roots
and why we're doing this i think
many companies and different industries
doesn't have to be in insurance
sometimes get into a rhythm and they're
successful things are going okay and
they don't change and
innovate and then it's too late um
and they're find themselves in in
financial stress and trying to work
their way out of it
so we were fortunate again with a being
a mutual company we were not constrained
by the same
um the same pressures that uh let's say
a quarterly stock company would have but
looking very short-term in nature
we can really look at that what's in the
long-term best interests of our
organization
our employees our community and when we
did that we said
um you know what when's the best time to
change it's actually when you're strong
when you're in a position of strength
and you know you heard me say earlier
we've grown from 150 to 500 million so
the company
is actually on a great path but what we
did was we looked out
ten years so rather than the next two to
three years and keep doing what we're
doing we said
well you know we all know the world's
changing at an exponential pace um
the pace of technological change
consumer
uh demands and expectations um you know
changes in demographics
climate change is a big one for us um so
when we look at
ten years and there's massive
consolidation and other things happening
we actually quite candidly said you know
if we don't transform
ourselves now we won't be capable to
compete
in that space 10 years out and that led
us to what we call our next horizon
strategic transformation there's a few
key components to it
our vision is to be a purpose-driven
digitally led national insurance company
and i think the purpose-driven piece
is really exciting for us particularly
for our employees
again back to our roots as a mutual
insurance company
we exist for a greater good than just
creating shareholder value so we can
really come to work every day
and have an impact in the world and so
the profits that we make as a mutual
company are reinvested in our business
and they're reinvested and redistributed
into the community
for a greater good so what we recognized
is
people don't understand today what um
a mutual insurance company is so there's
a role for us to modernize that value
proposition
uh and we're we're calling that our path
to purpose
the second piece of it what we refer to
as digitally led
is the transformation of our operating
model
and again this is going from very
traditional
business workflows and an operating
model to
redesigning all of our our internal
operating uh business workflows working
with
you know best in class partners like
mckinsey for example
who are looking at around the world and
saying you know this is the best
um in class uh specialization and
standardization that we can bring to
your business
so all of our workflows being changed
and
renovated for lack of a better word at
the same time
over two years we're replacing all of
our technology
and we'll be the first company in our
industry
to be completely on the cloud with our
uh core policy and management systems
so really trying to lead on the
technology front and then the third
piece of the transformation
which is the one i'm the most excited
about is our talent
and this again gets back to our opening
comments around our community and
um we are investing more in talent
than we've ever done before in the
history of this organization
um just to give you a sense of that
scale
we have a new executive team a new
leadership team
uh we have onboarded over a hundred new
people into this organization
just in the last 12 months alone and we
are on boarding another 100
in the next year so 200 people um
new to our organization excited to be a
part of our journey helping us with this
transformation
uh but i think back to your initial
question really it's really embracing
the concept of
changing when you don't need to change
you know trying to look out
in you know five ten years ahead of the
trends
and get yourself into a position so that
you're you're on the offensive versus
finding yourself in a defensive position
so there's a couple of things in there
maybe to
kind of go over the purpose driven i
mean
insurance is a global industry i mean
there are big players
um you talk about the growth that gore
has had and so finding that
what i still would say is a niche in the
canadian market and being what it is
which i think leads itself to you know
the importance of
why mutual and why still staying in this
community because it does lead to the
talent because we're close to talent
close to toronto and but technology is
another one that will drive where you
get your talent from because it's not
geographic based anymore
kovit has proven that for us or to us um
but but that technology change is back
in the day i mean i think
still you still have to have your little
pink slip for car insurance uh
i mean they're they're you know can't
even do that electronically
there are some things that are just so
antiquated
mostly government related government
regulation as opposed to industry but
are those the types of things you're
trying to get as better experience for
the end user better experience for the
broker network that sells your product
better experience for being for
answering questions better customer
service
because purpose driven i'm getting more
more talent being purpose driven here
and
and technology driven it sounds like
those things are all there's not
you can't have one without the other
they're they're sort of all all together
yeah great some great comments in there
and
and absolutely um in line with our
thinking i think the purpose driven
um piece has to be combined with a high
performing business model
so if you're a customer um you know
coming to us
what we hope in the end state when we're
finished our transformation is
we recognize as you say that insurance
isn't maybe the most exciting topic for
people
um but we all need insurance it plays a
critical role in society and in our
economy
and so you know as a purpose-driven
organization
we hope that when people select or they
feel that
there's actually some good like we're
trying to do some good in the world our
purpose statement is to provide
insurance that does
good um and there's three pillars under
that be good
do good and spread good and for example
be good is how we treat our internal
employees
you know leading in wellness initiatives
uh diversity and
inclusion spread good is you know how we
make an impact in our community and the
do good is
is really around what we're doing for
our policyholders and our customers and
i think
you raised a great point there our our
industry i would say
is like a decade behind
um some of the other financial
institutions like banking so you do your
banking you know on your phone
uh probably every day insurance is
lagging
but catching up in a hurry so there's
been a significant
investment uh globally in what they call
insure tech
the modernization of the insurance
platforms and
we've done a lot of work as you say on
customer and broker experience so
today we sell all of our products and we
will continue for many many years to
support our independent brokers of
seller products
but if you had that experience today it
wouldn't be very modern relative to some
of your other
experiences the technology that we now
have as an
industry so moving to um platforms like
the one that we're putting in place
gives us the ability to have direct
connectivity um
with the brokers and create a better
outcome for our customers so just to
give you
you know just like an example some of
the workflows that we have in place
you know in our previous operating model
would be
quite literally days of turnaround time
and we're moving to automated straight
through processing you know digital
um complete digital connectivity to our
brokers
we're also working with outside um
firms on experience like you like you
just referred to so what is the actual
experience
when you have a claim you know from the
customer's standpoint
in there i think amazing um progress is
being made so
through new technology platforms we have
you know we can respond
and measure that we're responding in you
know seconds and
less than a minute for example versus
you know previously just the
we didn't have the ability to do that so
i think there is a combination of the
purpose initiative which is if you have
to buy insurance
your money is actually going to make the
world a better place
including our investment portfolio where
we have a billion dollars where we're
really embracing esg
and making sure that the money is
invested in
in a way that is really thinking about
climate change
and making the world a better place and
then the experience itself
you know supported by a digital
transformation so that you
feel that you're getting that same
experience you might get in other
industries
when i think you're right with your
comments i think historically the
industry overall has
lagged um in terms of our ability to
provide that
for our customers so it's an exciting
time um
for our company for our industry for our
employees the type of
employment opportunities that that
creates is fantastic
so so you talked a little bit about this
your your growth
in your in your numbers at the at the
highest level
um but i think the reality it comes into
focus is you're expanding into the gta
so you're gonna have more of a toronto
focus um you've got
um you've got uh connections in western
canada
so you've got you're you're becoming
more of a big national player if you
will
with with different footprints in
different places
um and i think one of the things and and
we'll come to covent in just a minute
but i wanted to sort of asked about
you know as a as a regional uh insurer
and you want to be a national and you
are growing and you've demonstrated that
what's the importance of the gta and and
the other places to that to that growth
i mean
is it just totals the financial
marketplace or
center of the universe in canada you
just have to be there if you're for
if you're going to be part of growth is
that why toronto is an important part
yeah yeah great question there's a few
pieces to that
um that are really critical for us i
think you mentioned you know we are a
regional insurer and we our roots are
here
um in this community and so one of the
core principles that we've embraced is
we do want to go from being a
mid-sized regional insurer 500 million
to our our goal is actually we have 2
billion plus national insurers so four
times the scale we are today
um in order to do that we absolutely
need to have a presence
in the gta both from uh you know from a
talent
perspective um but also from a market
perspective so we historically have um
had a lot of our business outside of the
gta but if you think of
um just growth in population
the economy um there there's so much
expansion right here in ontario or right
down the road from us and
i think we'll talk about the corridor
and the importance of that as well
um so the gta is key you know i don't
believe we could be a
meaningful national player and not be in
the gta
but what we talk about is that doesn't
come at the expense of
being here in this region uh we're
actually doing both
so we um we see our and if you've ever
been here we have a spectacular
campus here in cambridge you know it's
been here
for many many years we're very fortunate
it's a beautiful property
so we are investing significantly in
this property i'm actually in the
building here today
to modernize the physical space here and
this will be
the location of an entirely new
operating model that we're launching
what we call our national contact center
so
cambridge will remain our head office
this is where i
come to work every day and a lot of our
executive team
it will be the core of our most of our
personal insurance
business and our national contact center
the
the offices that we have in vancouver
and the gta
will be more commercial lines focused as
well because of the nature of the
business
in those markets and we'll also use
those to attract
different type of talent that may live
in those regions um
we're also you know we'll talk a little
bit about the hybrid model that's coming
out of this
i think the key the key point there is
we're excited about
you know national expansion but
retaining our
our core roots in this community and
actually investing significantly in this
in this community still so so let's go
to that that hybrid model and i guess
the context i want to put this in which
is you may have been planning for this
right which it sounds like you this is
not something you woke up overnight
you've been working with the board
you've been looking for
what your new plan is and planning 10
years out so you've been planning on it
covid will have said thanks for your
plans
uh you better get going on it right now
because it's here right now like all of
us
how would we possibly work at uh with
everyone working at home
well we all figured out a way to do it
because you didn't have an option or
many did in you know i would say
insurance finance white collar not for
pro you know
you can work at home let's talk about
how covet has
accelerated those that change
that that you were already doing because
you didn't have the luxury of saying
we'll phase this in over three years
it's here and you're not going back on
that
um and i guess in the context of that
what are some of the positives that have
come from
that acceleration and what are some of
the things you've learned and said geez
that's not as
good for our business and we need to do
more work on it because it's
it's a mixed bag for everyone including
us as a chamber so maybe talk a little
bit about that hybrid model
but how covet has either accelerated or
really
um brought into focus the good and the
bad of
of what your plan was yeah yeah i think
i'm
excited to talk about this topic for
sure and i think you're right this is
not at all specific to insurance
necessarily this is something that every
call i'm on
is top of mind for every uh you know
everyone who's in
in a leadership position trying to
figure out how do we navigate through
this
i think if i step back just take us back
to the beginning of covet
so march of last year um
you know we all had no um no idea
that it was going to be this this
significant
i think the first reaction i i had was
you know just as as you did with your
organization and many others
in our community we actually moved
people to a virtual
model um within a matter of days and
you know we literally moved like 400
people
to a full virtual model and our brokers
moved to a full virtual model
and i can honestly say we didn't have
one
hiccup in terms of you know actually
running our business and i think
to your to your earlier point that would
be a big surprise certainly to me and to
many people
if you'd asked me like could we move 400
people work from home run the entire
industry
um from our basements in our pajamas you
know i'd say no way
like that i think that that the the fact
that we all had to do it at the same
time
created um the uniformity across the
platforms and everybody working in the
same way so i think that was the first
hurdle for us it was even more dynamic
because we had
just launched our strategy um that i
talked about so
in january we were all in this building
with you know
quite literally um hundreds of people
we're talking about running out of space
uh
physically we had consultants here and
we were doing you know daily
huddles and scrums and all the stuff you
do so we're so we're trying to figure
out how do you keep that going in a
virtual
space and then on top of that we have an
entirely new leadership team
um so it was it was an incredible time i
would say quite stressful
um in the early days if i transitioned
to kind of some of the benefits then
of the just pure not even getting the
hybrid yet but just to the pure
pandemic environment i think um
you know we brought in my example
earlier we brought 100 people on
during that period of time and a new
executive team some of them who started
the week of covet
um and it's ironic because we
i've never met many of these people
right and
like it's been over here now physically
you've never met them before i
physically met them right someone who's
in the office today
one of our leaders who i met for the
first time today it's been you know he's
been here for the whole
period of time right so that's just an
example but i know him
i know him so well because i actually
spend
almost every single day virtually online
so the one
benefit i think for us which is
interesting was
i actually feel like i know our
employees better and i've spent
more time with more employees because of
the ability to do that virtually if we
were in a traditional office
environment people tend to have habits
and processes and meetings
so that was one i think that was
interesting the other one i think
is the we had the benefit of focus
so with a strategy as big as what we
were working on
there was no debate about what the
priorities are and what we should be
working on
everybody knew exactly what the key
initiatives were
and i do think during a crisis sometimes
you can have a little bit of chaos um
you know and
we were fortunate we didn't have that we
also made the decision
really early on again i think this goes
back to our mutual
roots and taking that long-term view on
on the business model
to not um not stop anything but actually
increase the investment in our
transformation so
many times companies will run into a
crisis like this and they'll
they'll start cutting a head count or
cutting expenses or retrenching
we actually went out right away and said
no one will lose their jobs
employee wellness is our primary focus
making sure that we take care of our
people and actually we're going to
accelerate our investment
and try to innovate our way out of this
crisis with
faster digital technology investments
and other things as you say that
that came so quickly that we wouldn't
normally have come
i think the other impressive piece for
me is our broker distribution model
which even though i'd stand by my
earlier comments that were
we're all still a decade behind other
industries
very effective in the way that they
transition to
this model as well and serve clients
so overall i think the actual experience
was
quite good from a business perspective
which kind of leads to the hybrid model
which has been really
um interesting because i think
one of the questions that we're
struggling with and i think you are and
all of our
listeners maybe people are saying well
you've proven that it works um virtually
so why would i
have to ever come back to the office
again right so this is something we're
all struggling with
but we do see um some negatives
in this environment that we're trying to
address through the hybrid model
and some of the negatives i think again
not specific to our organization you
would feel them
and so would all of our our listeners
you know that how do you build a culture
when you've never met any of your your
peers right um there's something that
naturally happens when you're together
that's informal um conversations about
your family your friends your weekend
you don't set up a zoom call to like ask
about how the weekend went right
so that's one that we're worried about
and then i think
the other piece is we found that people
have worked harder
and longer hours virtually and then
combining that with
the pressures of young families
homeschooling
this has been very stressful for most of
our staff i would say many of our staff
so you know you hear a lot in the news
about well the office is dead and this
is all so great um we're all working
from home
i feel like there's a middle ground that
we're trying to find
where we acknowledge that it's actually
quite quite difficult to be virtually
all the time and there is a need for
human interaction
so we're working right now on this
hybrid model that if you visualize it
we're calling it
flexibility with a framework so
we will never go back to nine to five
everybody commuting to cambridge for
sure
but we do want people to be in the
office for certain
um rules you know certain roles actually
make sense to be in an office
for certain events and meetings and
training
and culture and so very early days but
we're trying to
really shape a model that has a bit of
the best of both worlds and with our um
with the gta with cambridge vancouver
and then the virtual technology we're
building
we think we can create something quite
um powerful for our employees
um in the next you know few months
yeah you know i think that's it that's
really important i i
you know with just about anyone who is
able now
obviously there's lots of your clients
and our members who are really hurting
because if you rely on
retail restaurants where people have to
come to your place of business it's a
different kettle of fish
although you know online and marketplace
and uh
curbside etc it will be part of what
they do moving forward but it's not in
the same way that we can
almost pivot entirely in the environment
that you have where you can do most of
it so
but but i i would say i think that's
very
i like to what would you say flexibility
with a framework because
i can't envision where we would ever go
back to nine to five
and have everyone into the chamber
office every day in fact
i won't do it i know i'm more productive
when i need to do my admin stuff i can
sit up sit at my desk and do this um
but i think you do miss something
there's something that it gets lost in
transmission looking at my screen
because i i know you and it's not the
same
as being in on the computer so i think
there is something to that
um but it leads to you know the
question i have if you accept that
there's going to be offices somewhere
and and
cambridge you've said is your home base
you know
your history and your roots are here um
maybe talk about some of the other
reasons i mean i i we're
we're very fortunate as a community to
have ufw
and laurier and conestoga you have
business students you got technical
students you've got
you know uh engineers computers and you
take your pick all the things if you're
if you're moving towards it you can get
the talent here and water the region
on the other hand um
you know in the in this new world you're
not confined
to just this region either i mean you
can say
you know some of your top talent could
be in other countries let alone other
provinces
um you know you know but there still is
a still
in many cases still have to have a home
base and you've chosen water your region
let me talk a little bit about about
drill into that particular part yeah
great
great comments um i think you're you're
right
like if i if i go back because i've been
here for as i said
over 15 years um
we as a regional player struggle
to attract and and sort of find
the talent we needed across our whole
organization because in
you know 15 years ago and what we were
looking for
um you know it was difficult because not
everyone wanted to live i fortunately
love this community and live here and i
have a great opportunity but that wasn't
the case right across the board
so some of our employees were commuting
from out of town
some of them lived here you have kind of
a mixed mixed bag
i think over the last decade having
grown up in the community
and i think we all see it um i mean this
is the most
one of the most exciting communities in
canada if not the fastest growing one so
there's so much
happening in this region today
that is so exciting um if you if you
live and work here and you're right i
mean we have
three um incredible uh
institutions here so we we've really
taken advantage of that so
we do have partnerships with with
laurier waterloo and
and conestoga is a fantastic
organization that
we have um co-op programs with so just
this week
i welcome just to give you a sense of
the volume
earlier this week i welcomed 30 um new
co-ops just for this
this term and i looked at the sheet and
the talent is just so impressive so it's
right across our organization from
technology
actuarial science finance insurance
so i think there's a bread of depth of
talent
here in this community that is just
incredible so we're really fortunate
with that
and your your comment's a good one
though you know i've heard this a few
times
in a way now the market is global um so
that change our view um
the other thing we've seen though that's
kind of counter to that which again is
favorable for this community
is many of many uh of our
talent and employees that lived in the
gta
and other major metro centers have
actually come
out and moved to areas like waterloo
region
for a better quality of life in some
ways the
work from home has
accelerated and we've seen that in the
real estate market out here people
wanting to say well hey i can work
in a new hybrid model i can live in
waterloo region
and i could maybe be in toronto for a
day a week and a couple days in the
cambridge office
and a couple days at home and so it's a
really dynamic
piece there so i think we have the best
of both worlds here which is
a tremendous talent to draw on from the
community and the students that are here
and also it's an attractive place to
live and raise a family
um so there's a great there's a great
dynamic happening
the other piece that's exciting for us
and you know one i know you've been
leading uh really a lot of work on the
um all day go transit trying to support
that
and we're a big supporter of that as
well that's another example of i think
just um you know how important that is
to if you listen to our story about
who we want to be we want to retain our
roots here but we want to expand into
the gta
i know i go into toronto quite a bit and
a six-hour drive round trip
is no fun for anybody even if you're
doing it one day a week so
i think that's a key point of that
culture right so the flexibility with a
frame
we see a model where we have our
employees connected
through uh initiatives like all-day go
transit so they can be in toronto for a
day
they can spend some days here i mean
it's such an amazing model
we're excited to see how that uh that
evolves yeah yeah that was a great
announcement that in the provincial
budget and last week
minister moroney effectively putting
some meat on the bones of
almost a billion dollar investment to
make sure that water to region
guelph cambridge waterloo brampton
milton
is connected to the gta so you can get
end-to-end without
in a you know in not 75 to 90 minutes
which you couldn't do that in the car
even if you tried
um but and but frequent so you could you
could make that trek in and out in
a convenient basis hugely important
because we
you know for all the reasons you talk
about the talent part of moving people
but as much as your your customers and
your clients are companies that are
working along the corridor right and so
getting
um getting people out of their cars onto
trains and getting
goods and services or goods to market
um on the roads which you need more i
mean it just makes all kinds of sense
and so the partnership we've had
with the business community like gore
and companies right across business
sectors
for the last three years saying this is
an infrastructure investment that is
good for every business sector
finance manufacturing uh services retail
take your pick
and so huge a huge uh uh win for all of
us
that we that we were we were able to
to move that forward so uh that's a
shout out to
all our businesses for that yeah it's so
exciting if you think about the um
you know the waterloo gta tech corridor
that's developing i think again it's
another link to our
our transformation in our company so i
think you and i talked a little bit
about
um insurance that's been a a an
important industry for
uh the waterloo region whether it's life
insurance or
pnc insurance but now we're going
through a transformation so
ensure tech and technology is actually
even more important so having that
technology base
here in waterloo region um it's it's
just so exciting
that the nature of the change that's
happening
in our industry and the link to insure
tech is a
really big connection for us as well so
we're fortunate that literally our
office is in the backyard
of you know canada's technology hub
right yeah
but you know what i think that's worth
diving into i know we
i've got a few more questions but i want
to take a couple of minutes to talk
about that
the change in and you talked about one
aspect which i think we all know is
natural disasters and climate change
impacts the insurance
sector so you know what you're paying
out what what those
those natural disasters that are more
frequent more intense what they're doing
to the insurance market
but the other part that is a seismic
shift is
the importance of of um it's almost a
more of a risk profile is as we become
more
technology-based ensuring what is
your intellectual capital and your data
capital if you will
if you describe it that way very
important and
you know um account insurance is one of
you know and
others that that are and many companies
would be in this saying
you better protect yourself you there
there's a there's business reasons you
need to protect yourself
is that a growing piece of of of what
you need to be uh
you know making available through your
broker network for for business
customers
yeah absolutely i think it's a great
comment i think
the products the solutions that our
industry is offering
are changing just as fast as the world
around us so
cyber insurance is is an offering that
we provide
to our small business customers and
i remember again five years ago um a lot
of talk about
cyber insurance being important and now
we're talking about it for personal
customers so
you know you're seeing more and more
identity theft
cyber attacks ransomware attacks
i would say in my history here at gore
again i was the chief risk officer in
the past as well
we talked about these risks but they
weren't
actually happening on a regular basis
and i would say
now today they are so there isn't a week
that goes by that we don't have a
conversation around a cyber attack
that's happened in our industry to our
company that we've been able to manage
so these are real risks for um you know
our policyholders as you say so there is
new products that we're offering and the
industry is offering to protect people's
data identity
from a cyber perspective the other
interesting area
is around usage-based insurance and
that's also been elevated
coming out of um kovid because people
don't use their cars for example to the
same extent that they used to
so you'll see more products and we'll be
offering them
as well where you know you can pay for
how much you use your
your car and if it's sitting in the
driveway and you're in this new
flexibility with a framework
hybrid model working for a company you
might only use your car twice a week
right so there is different
insurance products that are that are
being ruled out to reflect that
and same thing on the homeowners side
right like homes have now become
a home office um so what does that mean
from us
protecting people's cybers so you're
absolutely right
a lot of innovation happening um in the
space of insurance solutions for
customers
and the one thing we do find in our
brokers would be a big part
people don't always just have the
knowledge right um it's something that
you have to have yeah have to happen to
you before you worry about it so we've
got to do a better job of sharing that
information
making them affordable to people um and
making sure that they feel they're being
protected and i think that's such a good
important part it's part of the reason
that chambers exist i mean
you know as you and i talked about
before 75
of our members would have 10 or 15
employees or less like they're all
that's that's what business is it's
primarily small
very small medium-sized businesses and
they won't have that expertise which is
why we try and
let them know about things they should
be worrying about and ways to protect
themselves whether it's insurance or
otherwise so
that is an increasingly important one
that we do it's why we partner with
folks like gore
and others about saying how do you
manage your risk and protect yourself in
a cost-effective way
as a small business um this is
fascinating i'm enjoying this but
i i want to make sure i get through my
questions then i'm sure i'll have a a
few more at the end but
um i want to talk about about um
about the the foundation so they got the
you know and and the
the investments and i want to say
investments the um
the support you give to the community
and and your foundation
has made investments in health care and
education and
uh you know not-for-profits i want to
talk about because i think that you talk
about purpose-driven
uh you talk about the the things that
you're going to do
talk about what you have done and the
investments that have been made because
i think sometimes uh as as a canadians
and b
insurance we don't you do a particularly
good job of patting yourself on the back
but i think it's important for people to
understand
there is a gore foundation it's
investing in the community
and i think the expectation is you'll
continue to be investing in this
in this region where it's going to be
your home moving forward
as or continue to be your home as you
move forward
yeah thanks thanks ian um you know i
love this topic and and i think
the um you know the past we have
we've done amazing things with the
foundation uh
a real focus on supporting um you know
in a major
major way the local um healthcare uh you
know
both all of the hospitals for example um
doing meaningful contributions to the
hospitals
but what i found also interesting and i
think you see this every day you
mentioned our members are
our small business there are um you know
quite literally
you know hundreds if not thousands of
small organizations that need support
every
year and you know it could even be as
little as a thousand dollars to
five thousand dollars and we have been
there in the community with
you know hundreds and hundreds of these
organizations that we support every year
through
a range of contributions both the big
major programs like the hospitals and
the small
you know organizations that are kind of
the fabric of our community
and we've been really proud of that
specifically um
this year during the pandemic we
we embraced the term of leading with
purpose again so we
we said to ourselves you know when we
look back on this
this crisis you know in years to come
we want we will be measured as to how
did we behave
um as an as a corporate entity and how
do we treat our employees our
policyholders
and so we last year had a historic
donation
um a two million dollar canada helps
matching donation came out of the
foundation
directed right at the front lines
frontline responders and healthcare to
really try to be there to help and that
was a matching donation so the total was
over four million and again for a
company of our size and a foundation of
our size that was one of the largest
ones
in canada um so we're really proud of
that
going forward where i see this going
which is going to be
really exciting is allowing our members
to
shape the impact that we have and our
and our policyholders
um so if you think as a purpose-driven
organization
we we will have a number of initiatives
where we will have campaigns social
impact campaigns
you know what problems are we trying to
solve in the community
but also allowing our members to
particularly
vote or have an influence on where those
funds are redistributed
and i think we haven't done enough of
that in the past i'm linking
the work that the foundation and the
company is doing back to you as a
customer of course so again it
goes back to that purpose driven if you
buy a policy from us
you're going to get you know insurance
coverage it's going to be competitive
pricing but you know that your the funds
are being invested
in responsible ways in the investments
and also you can help shape what impact
we would have in our communities that we
live in which is really exciting
early days for us there we have a lot
more work to do on that but we think
that's going to be quite powerful for
our
for our customers and employees and
bring a lot of pride to
to our organization okay um
i want to ask uh
i know and i maybe maybe speak to this
uh um
while you're located in uh in cambridge
you've supported hospitals all three of
the hospitals
uh in from time to time as they've had
their capital campaigns the united way
across the waterloo region
local charities business organizations
um
i mean i think maybe just to put a maybe
uh
exclamation point you know water to
region as a whole it's not
cambridge you are supporting health care
in the region
education in the region um
not-for-profits in the region and i
think that's
you you've expressed that but that's
that's your your this home base is this
is this entire region and what it has to
offer
absolutely absolutely and even more
broadly
um like it's not a it's not just a
cambridge centric
focus it really is the communities that
our employees
live in um you know which is quite broad
um but absolutely the entire region of
of waterloo which is gorgeous and and
and we're in vancouver and we're in the
gta we'll be supporting those
communities as well
but it's certainly um you know the
impact we can have is quite meaningful
and wanting to make sure that we're
sharing that and spreading that
um in the communities that we that we do
business is really important to us
okay a couple of questions that have
come into the chat you can feel free to
punt on these because these are
fresh to all of us i i don't pretend to
understand what this one is
number of people living urban areas for
rural
do you see their potential growth for
farm mutuals and i i don't
kind of um i don't understand that so
maybe you can explain what that means
and
either yeah it's a great it's actually a
great question
um there are we're we are a mutual
insurance company but
uh we don't actually sell farm insurance
there are many companies that are
mutuals that are again
very important to the communities that
they're in so
air farmers mutual heartland is a is in
waterloo that's a
farmer's a farm mutual and um
i think that's like that's a great
comment i think that there is
there is a growth in the farming in
rural communities
and farm mutuals play a really important
role in those communities
and we do see some consolidation
happening there so
heartland is a good example it may have
merged with other farm mutuals to
make themselves stronger they're going
through the same challenges that we have
they have to invest in technology
they're looking for talent and they're
much smaller the farm mutuals
so i think there is a bright future for
farm mutuals
and they're the ones that are investing
in just as we are the future
and you are seeing actually a lot of
them doing that which is very
encouraging
cool okay um so the
question here if i get my glasses on
what are your suggestions for companies
who are looking to prepare
plans as they transition back into a
hybrid model what elements should they
be considering to plan for so
i think this is less on the insurance
side than you as a business
going into that into that hybrid and
actually i'm interested in this because
we're trying to figure out
when we go back probably in january ish
uh what does that look like and and
having a plan together what's
what's your advice to those thinking
about that yeah
yeah great question i can give you the
experience that we had which was
at first we um you know we got together
as a management team we started to talk
about it and
and what happened was and you may find
this in your organizations
everybody's bias started to come into
the the
the analysis so there's those that want
to work from home forever
would start to advocate for that model
some want everybody to come back to work
and so they're saying well this is just
a fad everybody's going to come back
into the office
and i could see very quickly that we
were going to find ourselves in a
position that wasn't
um healthy so what we did and again you
don't need to go outside i think to do
this we did actually partner with
with a consulting firm to help us go
through a process
um so that it was objective and not
biased by any individual executive or
leader
but i think you could do this just
internally quite easily
and i think there's a few key important
points to the first
one we did was we did engage our
employees so we went out and we surveyed
our employees we asked them
what their views on the future are how
they'd like to work
just so that we made sure we were
listening because it didn't make sense
to us to
roll something out that was completely
um you know blind to what the needs of
our employees were
so i think that's an important piece but
overlaying that
um this is where i was saying that there
needs to be
a bit of a focus on business performance
high performance so
we we actually looked at it by a role
and by
departments so each and every rule
what do you what's the best way that
rule should be shaped to drive the
outcomes that you're hoping to achieve
and if you feel that rule can be
effective working remotely then
that's great some roles clearly should
be together and
physically in the office some not so
much so i think they're
understanding it at the role level is
important and then the third piece is
the culture
so what culture are you trying to create
um
and again i don't think there's a right
or wrong answer because it's unique to
your
industry your company who you are there
are some companies who are saying
the office is really important to our
culture so we want
an office culture we want people to come
in on a regular basis
nothing wrong with that for their
organization others are saying
we think we can do this completely
virtually i know many of my peers and
others outside our industry too and then
that we're
we're somewhere in the middle where we
feel there's flexibility but we would
like a framework
we would like to have touch points where
we can be together
so i think those three pieces you know
engaging your employees thinking about
the
outcomes that's a it's a performance
mindset you're not letting the
biases describe the model but how do you
actually design a high performance model
and then also thinking about your
culture and what are you trying to
create as an organization
um and i think those three served us
quite well
that's uh that's good advice and uh
because we're going through the same
thing so i i hope uh
my team's watching this today we're
taking notes and we'll use those as
some of our guidelines okay but we've
got a couple of minutes left and then we
got to wrap
up um i i wanted to end
with not that it's necessarily important
um to everybody but your brand refresh i
think says a lot about what you
everything you've talked about you're
always trying to have in your tagline or
how you're going to market yourself
maybe talk about what your what your new
branding is going to be
because i think what it really does is
it talks about everything you've talked
about over the last hour
yeah yeah thank you and i think um you
know gore mutual
insurance you know has been our name for
181 years
but we recognize that it's you know we
don't have a modern value proposition
in the market so people don't really
understand what a mutual is they don't
understand insurance
and they and so our our purpose
direction which is to provide
insurance that does good so the future
brand refresh we'll still
we'll still have the name gore mutual
and it'll be a modern look and feel
with the tagline of insurance that does
good and then within that the three
pillars that i talked about
do good be good and spread good and i
think i think it allows us the
opportunity to have a conversation
around what we're referring to as the
modernization of the mutual model and
and you know what is different like why
would you buy
insurance from a mutual versus a company
that's a public company
and the fact that as a customer of gore
we have the ability to do good in the
world to redistribute
the premiums we take in to pay claims to
employ
people to give back to the communities
that we live in
and we think that's a powerful story
we're again we're early days on
developing that
but our new brand will have us really
reflect that concept of good
and the differentiation of the the
mutual model
and we're really excited about that
we're hoping to launch that later this
year
mid to late this year all right we're
going to leave it there
i want to thank you andy for joining us
today i really appreciate you taking
time out of your busy schedule because
it
sounds like you got a lot on your plate
so thank you for joining us today
thank you ian and thank you for having
me with my pleasure and uh
thank you for all the support and all
the great work that the chamber is doing
to help our
our community thanks so much okay and to
our title sponsor for the series
manulife
our platinum sponsor of the series the
immigration partnership of water to
region
to this month's presenting sponsor andy
and this and this team at gore mutual
insurance
and finally for all of you for joining
us today as a reminder we do host a new
business success series session every
wednesday at 1 pm
join us next week is andrew beeler
director of partnerships and learning
with the business and higher education
roundtable joins us for business
resources tools for working with
students
he'll be sharing a launch of a new work
integrated learning hub
resource hub that will provide business
with tools and resources to help them
maximize their experience working with
students
for all the details and register go to
greater kwchamber.com
please do share this series with your
friends and colleagues join us every
wednesday afternoon for another edition
of the business success series because
if it's wednesday
it's the business success series and
i'll leave you with this
uh please go if you're any small
business go to chambercheck.ca
get free rapid screening kits um and
free
medical grade masks all courtesy of the
cambridge and greater
kw chamber of commerce uh it's going to
be a while yet before we're through this
but get vaccinated but take care of
yourself your staff
so we can safely open and stay open
and remember to stay positive test
negative
because we're stronger together have a
great afternoon thanks everybody